Finding Aid for the Louis Jolyon West Papers LSC.0590
UCLA Library Special Collections
Louis Jolyon West papers
1890-1998
1948-1998
UCLA Library Special Collections
West, Louis Jolyon, 1924-1999
LSC.0590
106.0 Linear Feet (265 boxes)
Louis Jolyon (Jolly) West, M.D. (1924-1999) was a well-known Los Angles psychiatrist who served as the chair of UCLA's Department of Psychiatry and as director of the UCLA Neuropsychiatric Institute from 1969 to 1989. He was an expert on cults, coercive persuasion ("brainwashing"), alcoholism, drug abuse, violence, and terrorism. The collection contains Dr. West's research materials, lecture and presentation materials, personal and professional correspondence, and documents related to his professional associations and academic positions.
Conditions Governing on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Boxes 250-265 are closed due to HIPAA restrictions. In order to access materials that are protected under HIPAA (Health Insurance Portability and Accountability Act) or for which there is sensitive health information, please submit a research protocol to Library Special Collections at speccoll@library.ucla.edu.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
CONTAINS AUDIO MATERIALS: This collection contains both processed and unprocessed audiovisual materials. Audiovisual materials are not currently available for access, unless otherwise noted in a Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements note at the series and file levels. All requests to access processed digital materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9962185603606533
Biography/History
Louis Jolyon (Jolly) West, M.D. (1924-1999) was a well-known Los Angeles psychiatrist who served as the chair of UCLA's Department of Psychiatry and as director of the UCLA Neuropsychiatric Institute from 1969 to1989. He was an expert on cults, coercive persuasion ("brainwashing"), alcoholism, drug abuse, violence, and terrorism. He served as an expert witness in the trial of Patricia "Patty" Hearst, and examined Jack Ruby, the murderer of JFK assassin Lee Harvey Oswald.
Dr. West was born in New York City on October 6, 1924 and grew up in Madison, WI. After a year of college, he enlisted in the U.S. Army hoping to serve combat duty in World War II, but was instead sent to the State University of Iowa for Army Specialized Training in medicine. He met his wife, Kathryn "K" Louise Hopkirk in Iowa, and the two married on April 29, 1944. Together they had three children, Anne Kathryn, Mary Elizabeth, and John Stuart.
Dr. West continued his studies at the University Of Minnesota School Of Medicine, and received his M.D. in 1949. He completed his psychiatric residency at the Payne Whitney Clinic of the New York Hospital (Cornell Medical Center) in 1952.
Dr. West served Lieutenant to Major in the U.S. Air Force from 1948 to 1956, and after completing his residency at Payne Whitney, he became the Chief of Psychiatric Service at the 3700th USAF Hospital at the Lackland Air Force Base. At Lackland he worked with returning POWs from the Korean War who had falsely confessed to germ warfare. His experiences with these men sparked a lifelong interest in helping victims of imprisonment, torture, and coercive persuasion ("brainwashing"). He also helped develop a highly successful method of alcoholism treatment dubbed "The Lackland Model," and he took a humanitarian approach to understanding homosexuality in the military.
In 1954, at only 29, Dr. West was appointed professor and chair of the Department of Psychiatry at the University of Oklahoma, being "perhaps the youngest full professor in an American medical school." In Oklahoma City he demonstrated his support of the civil rights movement by attending sit-ins and rallies, and bringing along his friend, actor Charlton Heston, to aid in the publicity of such events.
Dr. West's research interests continually expanded, always incorporating the changes taking place in society. During a 1962 study on the effects of LSD on a bull elephant, Dr. West and his colleagues accidently killed the elephant by administering too high of a dosage of either LSD or a tranquilizer. This incident was often brought up by his adversaries when they attempted to portray him as irresponsible and as a "crack pot." In 1967, he led a group of researchers to San Francisco's Haight-Ashbury district where they rented an apartment and studied the hippie culture, particularly as it related to sex and drugs.
In 1969, Dr. West seized the opportunity to move to Los Angeles and become the chair of UCLA's Department of Psychiatry and director of the UCLA Neuropsychiatric Institute. In terms of his research interests, Dr. West felt that a rapidly expanding and diverse city like Los Angeles was most appropriate. Shortly after arriving at UCLA, he set out to create a "Center for the Study and Reduction in Violence," "the world's first and only center for the study of interpersonal violence." His plans for the Center were never actually realized because there was "such an outcry against it?based on arguments that to study violence was essentially to experiment on underprivileged people,?, doing brain operations, putting electrodes in their heads, or making guinea pigs out of them… This was the most frustrating experience of my career."
Dr. West's career included many remarkable events, including his participation in the highly-publicized 1976 trial of newspaper heiress Patricia "Patty" Hearst. Dr. West, an expert on coercive persuasion, testified for the defense that Ms. Hearst was not in her right mind when she participated in the bank robbery with the Symbionese Liberation Army (SLA). In 1977, he traveled to South Africa to testify on behalf of a group of Zulus who had been forced, through torture and other inhumane tactics, to confess to crimes they did not commit. He returned to South Africa in 1983 and 1984 to testify on behalf of a political prisoner suffering from post-traumatic stress.
Throughout his career Dr. West was interviewed for newspaper articles and television reports on a variety of topics including cults, coercive persuasion, violence, alcoholism and drug abuse, kidnapping and terrorism. He received many honors including a 1959 nomination as one of the "Ten Most Outstanding Young Men in America," the 1973 Benjamin Rush Gold Medal Award from the American Psychiatric Association, a dedication--the "Louis Jolyon West House" treatment facility at the Oklahoma Center for Alcohol-Related Studies, the 1987 Vestermark Award from the American Psychiatric Association and the National Institute of Mental Health, the 1989 Leo J. Ryan Award from the National Cult Awareness Network, and in 1990 an Honorary Doctor of Humane Letters from the Hebrew Union College.
West retired from his positions as chair and director in 1989, but continued as a professor in the Psychiatry department, and continued to write articles and present papers at conferences around the world. West passed away on January 2, 1999 at the age of 74. In 2009, his son, John Stuart West published a memoir about being asked to assist in the suicides of each of his parents, Jolly and K.
1 Dean of Oklahoma medical school
2 West quoted in the Los Angeles Times, 1985
3 Ibid.
Scope and Content
The collection consists primarily of paper materials, but also includes newspaper and magazine clippings, audio cassette recordings, and slides. The collection includes research materials; lecture and slide presentation materials; writing; correspondence with colleagues and friends; materials related to his involvement in professional organizations; and materials related to his positions as chair of the UCLA Department of Psychiatry and director of the Neuropsychiatric Institute. Dr. West's collected newspaper and magazine clippings related to a vast array of research interests, and clipped seemingly every newspaper and magazine article regarding the Patty Hearst case between 1975 and 1977. The collection does not contain any of Dr. West's patient records.
Organization and Arrangement
The collection is organized into seven series: Lectures, Writing, Office Files, Personal, Professional Activities, Academic Career, and Research Files.
Series 1. Lectures. Materials are grouped according to the subject of the lecture. The materials include slides and notes about slides, research materials, travel information and correspondence related to presentations, audio recordings and transcripts. Related materials can be found in Professional Activities and Research Materials. Filing sequence is by contents: Slide materials (no slides) --> Slides and slide materials'Slides only, contains slides people, facilities, and celebrations at UCLA --> Audio cassettes, reel tapes and transcripts.
Series 2. Writing. Folders are named according to title or subject of writing, or publication the writing was intended for. Folders include correspondence and research materials. See related materials in Professional Activities and Research Materials.
Series 3. Office Files. Contains three subseries:
3.1 LJW in the Media. Contains newspaper clippings and articles about LJW or where LJW was interviewed and media contacts.
3.2 Consultation. Contains materials related to legal cases where LJW has been asked to consult
3.3 Correspondence. Contains correspondence to and from LJW, primarily with professional colleagues.
Materials are grouped by year, by first letter of the last name of correspondent, and by last name of correspondent.
Series 4. Personal. Contains correspondence of a personal nature with LJW's family and friends and military orders
Series 5. Professional Activities. Contains eight subseries with materials related to each professional organization and activities:
5.1 American Association of Chairmen of Departments of Psychiatry (AACDP)
5.2 American College of Neuropsychopharmacology
5.3 American Psychiatric Association (APA)
5.4 California Medical Association (CMA)
5.5 Center for Advanced Studies in Behavioral Sciences
5.6 Department of Veterans Affairs (VA)
5.7 Miscellaneous professional activities. Contains materials related to smaller organizations and onetime events.
5.8 National Institute of Mental Health (NIMH)
Series 6. Academic Career. Contains six subseries.
6.1 UCLA-LJW's Committees, activities, teaching, and grant applications
6.2 UCLA-LJW's Promotions, sabbaticals, and retirement
6.3 UCLA Center for Preventive Psychiatry
6.4 UCLA Center for the Study and Reduction of Violence (CSRV)
6.5 UCLA Neuropsychiatric Institute (NPI)
6.6 University of Oklahoma
Series 7. Research Files. Contains three subseries.
7.1 Research A to Z-Materials are arranged alphabetically by subject area.
7.2 Cults
7.3 Newspaper clippings
West, Louis Jolyon, 1924-1999 -- Archives
- 1. Lectures and Slides., 1957-1996.
  Scope and Contents note
  The Lectures and Slides series contains slides, notes about slides, and research materials on a variety of subjects. This series also contains correspondence and travel information related to presentations and audio cassette and reel-tape recordings of presentations. See Writing series, Professional Associations, and Research Files series for related materials.
  - Lecture Abstracts., 1976, 1982, 1986, undated. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Abstracts of miscellaneous lectures used for sending with proposals. Includes some correspondence.
  - "Epidemiology of Violence.", 1982 October 29-November 8. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Prepared for the American Medical Writers Association (AMWA) in Los Angeles, CA October 26-30, 1982.
  - Alcoholism lectures., 1982, undated. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Various talks on alcoholism. Includes notes on Abipone Indians and a published article on Controlled Drinking
  - "Abstinence Versus Controlled Drinking"., ca. 1981. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Includes cassette tape recording and typed transcription of lecture presented at the 2nd Annual Institute of Alcohol and Drug problems. Circa 1981.
  - "Dissociation, Possession, and Abduction by Aliens"., 1994 March 29-July 27. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Prepared for the II World Psychotherapy Congress in Bali, Indonesia July 25-27, 1994.
  - "Psychiatry and Scientology"., 1991 June 14-1992 May 6. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Prepared for the American Psychiatric Association "Distinguished Psychiatrist" Lecture, Washington, DC May 6, 1992. Includes correspondence with American Family Foundation.
  - "LSD, Clinical Manifestations"., 1974, 1991. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Prepared for the Drug Enforcement Administration (DEA) LSD Conference in San Francisco, CA December 10, 1991.
  - "The Psychobiology of Collective Violence: Implications for Prevention"., 1991 October 31- 1992 November 11. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Prepared for the World Congress on Violence and Human Coexistence in Montreal, Canada July 13, 1992.
  - "Psychobiology of Violent Behavior in Humans"., 1992 October 10. (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Prepared for the Annual Meeting of the Pavlovian Society of North America, Los Angeles, CA October 10, 1992.
  - "Health Consequences of Human-Induced Trauma: An Overview"., 1992 October 25. (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Prepared for the International Society for Traumatic Stress Studies (ISTSS) Annual Meeting, Los Angeles, CA October 25, 1992.
  - "Traumatic Stress in Pathogenesis of Pseudo-Identity"., 1992 October 25. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - "Pseudo-Identity: A Form of Personality Change"., 1992 August 14-1993 May 27. (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Prepared for the American Psychiatric Association Annual Meeting in San Francisco, CA May 22-27, 1993.
  - "The Scientology Wars"., 1992 November 7. (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Prepared for the Keynote address at the Cult Awareness Network (CAN) Annual Meeting November 7, 1992. Folder includes a writing "Scientology's Harassment of L.J. West"
  - "Cults: A Public Health Approach"., 1981 November 20-22. (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Presented at the International Conference on the Effects of New Totalitarian Religious and Pseudo-Religious Movements on Society and Health in Bonn, West Germany November 20-22, 1981. Handwritten on folder: "Cults: A public health approach AKA Cults: Strange bedfellows"
  - Cults lecture., 1981 June 12. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Presented at the "Conference on Conversion, Coercion and Commitment in New Religious Movements," Berkeley, CA June 12, 1981.
  - Death penalty lectures., 1961 December 26- 1967 March 6. (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Folder includes "Scientific Reflections on the Death Penalty" for presentation at the Center for the Study of Democratic Institutions, Santa Barbara, CA March 6, 1967, "A Psychiatrist Looks at the Death Penalty" presented at the 122nd Annual Meeting of the American Psychiatric Association, Atlantic City, NJ May 11, 1966, and "An Open Letter to The People of Israel" regarding the death penalty for Adolf Eichmann.
  - "Cults and Their Apologists: Strange Bedfellows"., 1982 April 18-1983 October 31. (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Prepared for the conference on "Conversion, Coercion and Commitment in New Religious Movements," Berkeley, CA June 12, 1981 and the UNEX Conference on "The Cult Phenomenon: Mental Health, Legal and Religious Aspects," UCLA April 18, 1982. Handwritten "NPI Colloq, 10-31-83"
  - "Cults, Violence, and the Media"., 1983 May 3-4. (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Prepared for the American Academy of Psychoanalysis May 3, 1984.
  - Violence lectures., 1969, 1987, 1980. (Box 2, Folder 3)
    For presentation at the American Psychiatric Association (APA) Annual Meeting in May 1980. Folder includes "Sanity in the Sierra Madre: The Tarahumara Indians" presented at APA Annual Meeting in Miami Beach, FL May 1969.
  - "Terrorism, Torture, and the American Psychiatrist"., 1987 May 11. (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Presentation given upon receiving the Seymour Vestermark Award at the American Psychiatric Association Annual Meeting in Chicago, IL May 11, 1987. Folder contains cassette tape recording of Vestermark lecture and typed transcription.
  - "Setting the Problem"., 1973 June 28- 1977 July 12. (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Folder includes correspondence regarding the publication of the proceedings from the Kittay Scientific Foundations Fourth International Symposium and includes the transcription of LJW's presentation "Setting the Problem." Proceedings published as G. Serban (Ed.), "New Trends in the Community Setting." (1977)
  - Dissociative Disorders--speech material., 1967-1978. (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Folder includes LJW's book chapter "Dissociative Reaction," from the Comprehensive Textbook of Psychiatry, edited by Alfred M. Freedman, M.D. and Harold I. Kaplan, M.D.,(1967) LJW's "Seminar Notes: The Dissociative Reactions Revisited," and presentation outline. The folder also contains correspondence with Michael Sheehy and Robert Spitzer of the APA Task Force on Nomenclature and Statistics regarding LJW's involvement in the revised definition of the Dissociative Disorders for the DSM-III. One letter suggests that Multiple Personality Disorder be considered as a separate diagnostic category from Hysteria.
  - "Psychodynamics of Violence"., 1963-1980. (Box 2, Folder 7)
    For presentation at the American Psychiatric Association Annual Meeting in San Francisco, CA May 6, 1980. Folder contains several of LJW's published articles on violence.
  - "Why Does Terrorism Terrorize?"., 1980 January 11-May 4. (Box 2, Folder 8)
    Correspondence and articles related to panel discussion LJW participated in at the American Academy of Psychoanalysis Annual Meeting in San Francisco, CA May 1-4, 1980.
  - "The Psychobiology of the Pogrom"., 1982 May 26-June 3. (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Folder includes transcription of presentation given to the Association for Mental Health Affiliation with Israel on May 26, 1982.
  - "Violence"., 1978 February 2-December 11. (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Transcript from LJW's remarks at the Conference on the UCLA Case Study Workshop sponsored by The Hastings Center February 2-3, 1978.
  - "Mental Illness: An American Dilemma"., 1990 May 14. (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Commencement address given at the Hebrew Union College in Los Angeles, CA May 14, 1990
  - "Methods of Psychotherapy"., undated. (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - "Methods of Detention and the Effects of Isolation on the Evidence of Detainees"., 1982 August 6-November 10. (Box 3, Folder 3)
    Folder includes cassette tape recording and transcription of presentation given in South Africa in September 1982. Folder also includes correspondence regarding LJW's contribution of a book chapter on hallucination for the "Clinical neuropsychology" volume of the Handbook of Clinical Neurology.
  - "Research on Violence, Problems and Possibilities"., 1973 October 31. (Box 3, Folder 4)
    Presented at the Mental Health Development Commission of Los Angeles County at its meeting on October 31, 1973.
  - "Rachmaninoff and Dr. Dahl"., 1982 February 12. (Box 3, Folder 5)
    Presented at the Winter half-day meeting February 12, 1982.
  - Terrorism--Speech material., undated. (Box 3, Folder 6)
    Folder includes "The origins of political terrorism: A research proposal" (Knutson) and a summary of "The Psychodynamics of Terrorism" for presentation on May 20.
  - "Occupational Stress"., 1972 September- 1975 April. (Box 3, Folder 7)
    Folder includes typed transcription of LJW's paper given at the Cornell Conference on Job Stress, September 1972 and correspondence regarding LJW's contribution to Dr. Alan A. McLean's book "Occupational Stress." Also includes two issues of the journal Occupational Mental Health.
  - "Marginal Psychotherapies"., 1981 March 16-July 20. (Box 3, Folder 8)
    Folder includes cassette tape recording and transcription of presentation given to the California Medical Association on March 16, 1981. Recorded by Audio-Digest.
  - "'Brainwashing, Behavioral Control and the Risk of Harm"., 1989 May 4-October 13. (Box 3, Folder 9)
    Prepared for the American Bar Association's National Institute on Tort and Religion in San Francisco, CA. Program titled "Tort Liability for Brainwashing: A Debate" May 4-5 1989.
  - "The Psychiatrist in the Courtroom"., 1977 September-1978 June 15. (Box 3, Folder 10)
    Folder includes transcript of presentation given at the First Regional Congress of Social Psychiatry in Santa Barbara September 1977.
  - "Jack Ruby"., 1978 October 30. (Box 3, Folder 11)
    Folder contains cassette tape recording and typed transcription of LJW's presentation on Jack Ruby given at the UCLA Neuropsychiatric Institute Colloquium October 30, 1978.
  - "Hypnosis"., 1981 October-1982 January. (Box 4, Folder 1)
    Seminar given Winter Quarter 1982. Includes syllabus dated January 1982.
  - Miscellaneous transcriptions., 1961 September 17-October 13, 1965 February 6. (Box 4, Folder 2)
    Folder includes transcription of LJW's speech given to the Board for Texas State Hospitals and Special Schools (1965) and transcription of LJW's speech for the Annual Washington State Medical Association Civil Disaster meeting, September 17, 1961.
  - Miscellaneous speech materials., 1982 January 25. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Sam Smith--speech and slide material., 1976 May 25-1989 May 11. (Box 4, Folder 4)
    Folder contains correspondence and materials pertaining to Samuel Mitchel Smith, M.D. of Columbus, OH. Material may have been used for LJW's farewell address to the APA Chairmen of Departments of Psychiatry
  - Right To Die--slide material., 1990 October 25. (Box 4, Folder 5)
    Contains notes, slide negatives, slides (1 page) and cassette recording of LJW's talk.
  - Alcohol and Drug Abuse--slide material (Folder 1 of 2)., undated. (Box 4, Folder 6)
    Folder contains keys for slide presentations, slide negatives, and newspaper clippings.
  - Alcohol and Drug Abuse--slide material (Folder 2 of 2)., 1990, undated. (Box 4, Folder 7)
    Folder contains slides (6 pages) "Chemical abuse and dependencies" (with notes) which may have been presented at Grand Rounds Harbor-UCLA (June 10-no year given), "Alcoholism," and "DUI/Accidents," marijuana statistics (1990).
  - Terrorism--slide material., undated. (Box 4, Folder 8)
    Folder contains slides "Terrorism" (4 pages ), "Terrorism" (1 page), "Terrorism duplicates" (1 page), and "New Vestermark slides" (1 page). Also see "Torture-- slide materials".
  - Witches and Aliens--slide material., undated. (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Torture--slide material., undated. (Box 4, Folder 10)
    Folder contains 3 pages of slides
  - History of Psychiatry and Mental Health Services--slide material., undated. (Box 4, Folder 11)
    Folder contains slides "History of psychiatry, mental health services" (3 pages, and key), and "Mental health services history (dupes)" (2 pages).
  - Mesmer, Hypnosis, Dissociation- slide materials., undated. (Box 5, Folder 1)
    Folder contains slides (3 pages) and slide keys for presentations
  - Mind Control, Influence, Brainwashing--slide material., undated. (Box 5, Folder 2)
    2 pages of slides
  - Trauma--slide material., 1996 March 30, undated. (Box 5, Folder 3)
    Folder contains slides "Psychiatric challenges of trauma, March 30, 1996" (2 pages), "Health consequences of trauma" (1 page), "Prevalence of Post-traumatic Stress Disorder (PTSD), Violence of Terrorism" (1 page) and slide negatives.
  - Cults--slide material., undated. (Box 5, Folder 4)
    Folder contains slides "Cults" (2 pages), Untitled slides [violence and cults] (3 pages), cult leaders (1 page), Cults/Satan/SLA ( 1 page).
  - LSD, The Haight, Hallucinations- slide material., undated. (Box 5, Folder 5)
    Folder contains slides "LSD and The Haight (4 pages), "Haight-Ashbury Hallucinations" (2 pages), and 1 slide of elephant, likely from LSD experiment
  - Drug Testing- slide material., undated. (Box 5, Folder 6)